Exercise 4.
Reflection. The Hall of Mirrors. The Left Hand Path.
Find a quiet, comfortable place. Relax your body and clear your
mind.
Let go of your fears and your fantasies.
They will deceive you if you let them.
You close your eyes and imagine that the gold and silver chain
is clasped around your neck and that the key is hanging over
your heart.
You imagine yourself grasping the key and holding it tightly in
your hand.
You feel the power of the key's energy growing stronger as you
hold it. As the power of the key's energy increases, you feel
it pulling you away from the earthly plane.
You feel yourself drifting slowly downward, away from the
mundane world.
With every beat of your heart, you drift ever closer to the
shadow realm.
you are now nearing the borders of the shadow realm you are
very close the key begins to grow warmer in your hand without
warning it suddenly becomes burning hot you release your hold on
the key but as you do the clasp on the necklace breaks
and the key and the necklace fall into into the Shadow Realm
below you.
You look at the palm of your hand. An imprint of the
key has been burned into your flesh.
You resume your descent, and you pass over the borders and enter
into the Shadow Realm.
Instead of the usual twilight, you are greeted by a nearly pitch
black world.
You hover in the air high above the darkness. darkness. Soon,
you are able to see an eerie glow of crimson light breaking
on the horizon, and, as you watch, a blood -red crescent moon
rises high into the skies of the shadow realm.
But it is not the light of the sun reflecting off of
the moon that is creating the shape of the crescent. The moon
has been almost completely destroyed.
Huge chunks of what remain of the moon flow aimlessly about the
jagged blood -red crescent of the destroyed moon.
Now, rising into the sky far off on the horizon, you see
what is creating the eerie crimson glow on what remains of the
moon.
The sun has become a dying red dwarf star.
Its crimson light is muted and vague.
You can now hear distant screams and ghostly cries echoing from
somewhere deep within the blackness of the shadow realm below
you. you.
Distant thunder rolls across the horizon, and the air of the
Shadow Realm is charged with wild energies.
Ghostly flashes of St. Elmo's fire appear and disappear below
you in the blackness of the Shadow Realm.
You now hear a vague, but very unsettling, cracking sound far
off in the distance. It is as if some huge unseen creature
was slowly moving towards you in the darkness.
You notice the glow of a faint yet constant red light far
below you. You are somehow being drawn towards this red light.
You resume your descent and slowly float down into the
blackness.
As you begin to approach the center of the shadow In the
shadow realm, you can now see vague outlines and shapes in the
glow of the blood red moonlight.
You are drifting toward the crystalline spheres of the two
circles of power.
The circles have been smashed to pieces.
Some incredibly powerful force has destroyed the circles.
Pieces of the walls of the circle remain intact, but they jut
out in sharp jagged edges like two huge broken snow globes.
As you float into the center of the smashed circles, your feet
touch down on the white marble floor beneath you.
You can hear a subtle rustling sound all around you. You feel
as though someone or something were watching you.
You can see that the constant glow of red light is now
only a few yards away from you,
but the source of the red light is still hidden in the
darkness. darkness.
You take several small, cautious steps towards the red light.
Small pieces of the smashed circle crunch beneath your feet.
Whatever was rustling around in the darkness stops moving.
The entire shadow realm becomes eerily quiet.
A haunted feeling washes over you. Slowly, carefully, you
continue to move towards the the glow of red light.
But as you approach it, you are frozen in your tracks.
You are suddenly able to see the horrors revealed in that awful
crimson glow.
The griffon lies dead on the ground.
The animal has been ripped to pieces from the inside out. It
is as if the eagle and the lion had tried to separate
themselves from each other and that they tore themselves apart
in the process.
A stream of slick black blood flows from the body of the
fallen beast. It pools beneath your feet.
Next to the still and silent body of the griffon, you see
that someone or something has written the words, Welcome to the
Nightmarelands in blood, on the white marble floor of the Shadow
Realm.
The bloody tracks of a large bird lead off into the darkness.
Your blood runs cold through your veins.
Something suddenly hisses at you. As you turn to face this new
horror, your feet slip in the bloody pool under your feet. You
fall backwards into the pool of crimson gore.
Frozen with fear, you see a pair of huge glowing red eyes
staring at you from out of the darkness.
Now a huge Cheshire grin of sharp white teeth smiles at you
from the shadows.
smoke and flame issue from flared nostrils and a clawed and
scaly hand thrusts the bloody carcass of a dead lamb at you
it shakes the carcass a few times to make sure you notice
then the thing in the shadows turns and runs away into the
darkness
you can hear its laughter echoing throughout the wreckage of
your domain
it was the dragon and he has become an insane killer killer.
The shadow realm has become a land of nightmares and madness.
You carefully regain your feet and peer around in the darkness
for any signs of movement.
You see nothing.
You return your attention to the red glow. It is now only
a few feet away from you.
Carefully, carefully, you move toward it.
Now, you can see that it is a glowing red crystal of
many facets.
The faceted crystal is lying on the white marble floor, directly
in front of the mirror.
You see that the looking glass of the mirror has been smashed
and its pieces are also scattered on the marble floor.
As you bend down and reach for the glowing red crystal, you
touch a shard of the broken looking glass.
It slices your fingertip open. You are bleeding. Your blood is
dripping from this open wound, and the droplets of your blood
fall to the ground and mix with the blood of the griffin.
As the two bloods mix together, something very strange begins to
happen.
The mixed blood at your feet begins to swirl. It begins to
flow on a stream toward the base of the mirror frame.
There's more blood than you thought.
The stream of blood shimmers with the eerie light of the
crystal's red glow. glow. It surges up the side of the mirror
like a crimson tide, and it fills the empty space inside the
frame with a looking glass of living blood.
You see a sudden flash of light at your feet.
Something is sparkling in the pool of blood.
It is the Soul Sword.
You can just discern that its blade has been broken in half.
You You also see that the lost necklace and key are wrapped
around the hilt of the sword.
You bend down and reach for the necklace and the key, but
your wrists are suddenly seized by some powerful unseen force
and you are jerked into the air.
Something holds your wrists.
You are dangling above the blood -stained floor of the Shadow
Realm.
You twist your body and pull your arms in an effort to
free yourself, but your strength Your strength is useless
against the powerful invisible force holding you in its grasp.
A horribly painful image flashes through your mind. This same
image appears on the surface of the looking glass of blood.
Your memory stirs. In your mind, you now see the worst thing
that you have ever done to another person.
This memory replays itself on the looking glass of living blood.
You must watch it as it plays, over and over again.
Unable to move, you are forced to watch your own cruelty.
cruelty.
Your memory stirs again and now in your mind you see the
worst thing that has ever happened to you.
Like your first memory, this memory too replays itself on the
looking glass of living blood.
You must watch it as it plays. You feel your remembered pain,
humiliation, and sadness all over again.
Unable to move, you must keep watching, feeling, remembering.
Now,
an image of the thing that you are most afraid of flashes
through your mind.
The worst possible outcome of this fear plays itself out on the
looking glass of living blood.
You must watch it as it plays and replays. You want to
run, but the unknown force holds you motionless. You are unable
to move. You cannot flee.
You look at your reflection in the looking glass of living
blood.
What do you see?
the deepest, darkest parts of your mind.
You look into the looking glass of living blood, and you see
your soul reflected upon its surface.
You cannot move. You are totally in the power of the unknown
force that is holding you before the looking glass.
You must face these awful parts of yourself.
You are unable to move. You cannot turn away from yourself.
There is nothing on earth or in any other realm that you
can do. do. You must face yourself. You must face your own
cruelty, your humiliation, your fear.
You have no choice. You are required to look at yourself, face
to face, in the looking glass of living blood.
regard your mind regard your soul you have now faced the dark
mirror of self
the broken blade of the soul sword floats up and away from
the blood -stained floor of the shadow realm it rises into the
air directly in front of you you see that the necklace and
the key are still dangling from the hilt of the sword the
broken half blade of the soul sword sword lunges at your chest.
It pierces you through the heart. You feel no pain.
What you feel is the intense heat of a purifying fire burning
away inside you. There is no blood, but you feel as if
your life force were draining away. away.
Like the shamans of old, you are now dead.
Like all shamans, you must be reborn into the light and reclaim
your power.
Slowly, the broken blade of the soul sword pulls itself out of
your chest and returns turns to the blood -stained floor from
which it came.
It takes the necklace and the key with it.
The bloody surface of the looking glass begins to spin in a
dark vortex of power and energy.
Its pull is intense and undeniable.
Suddenly, the unseen force that is holding you aloft releases
its grip.
You are instantly pulled into the dark spinning vortex of the
looking glass. glass.
You are now gliding through a pitch black tunnel at incredible
speed. You are traveling through a dark and twisting pipeline.
You are speeding through a small space without sound or light.
You are totally alone in the dark.
As you glide through the twists and turns of the tunnel you
somehow realize that you are leaving your old life behind
The person that you were fades away in the darkness behind you
Now you are becoming much more than you ever were before
You can now see a vague light in the distance far ahead
of you. As you glide closer to this light, you see that
it shimmers and shines in a dawning aurora of color.
You have seen this light before. It is the living waters of
the sun side of the looking glass.
You have entered the portal of the mirror from one side, and
now you are going to exit from the other side.
Instead of a portal to the astral plane or to another dimension,
dimension. The empty space between the two sides of the Looking
Glass has become a canal of darkness.
It is taking you to your destiny.
You glide through the final turn of the tunnel.
Now, you plunge through the living waters of the Looking Glass.
As you pass through the sun side of the mirror, you feel
as though though your body were somehow absorbing the light in
the unknowable waters of the looking glass.
You feel as though your entire being has become fluid.
You raise a liquid hand in the air in front of your
eyes, and you are amazed by what you see.
The surface of your hand shimmers and shines with the reflective
light of the living waters of the looking glass.
You can see your own reflection in the palm of your hand.
You see that your entire body has somehow been transformed into
a living mirror.
Other than yourself, however, nothing else is being reflected
onto the mirrored surface of your body.
You are now back where you began your journey through the
labyrinths of balance.
You are back inside the void. void.
You look around and you can see nothing. You can feel nothing.
The mirrored surface that your body has become reflects only the
nothingness of the void.
This is, you realize, your chance to start over again. You have
been reborn. born.
The void that surrounds you is the womb of a new beginning.
As you think about this, you also realize that it is what
you have accomplished in the past that has led you to this
new beginning.
The shadow realm is the symbol of your accomplishments, but the
shadow realm that you left behind is under the control of dark
powers and forces.
It has become unbalanced.
You know that you must return to the shadow realm and restore
it.
But how?
You look around at the vastness of the void.
It is limitless, and it is empty.
There is only nothingness, no mirror, no exit, no way out.
You know that you yourself have become the living waters of the
looking glass.
How can you pass through yourself?
As you hold your mirrored hands in front of your eyes, you
begin to realize that you cannot pass through yourself.
but what you see in the palm of your mirrored hand sparks
an idea.
The imprint of the key is still burned into the palm of
your hand.
You run your fingertips over the imprint and sense that not only
has the key left behind its mark, but it has also left
behind some of its magic.
When last you saw them, the key and the necklace were wrapped
around the hilt of the soul sword. Broken or not, you know
that there is also powerful magic within the Soul Sword. The
powerful magic of creation.
Focusing your mind, you concentrate on the imprint of the key
burned into the palm of your hand.
You call for the key to return to you.
Instantly, you feel the key and the necklace rising up through
the living waters of your body.
But there is also something else. The spirit of the soul sword
is returning to you as well.
The key, the necklace, and the spirit of the soul sword pass
through the living waters of the palm of your hand, and you
grasp the hilt of the sword.
Its power and magic are still intact. tact.
It feels good to be holding the spirit of the soul sword
in your hand once again. Its presence and power boost your
confidence even higher.
The key and the necklace float in the void directly in front
of you.
As if it had been given a silent command, the key pivots
and turns, thrusts forward through the air, and begins turning
as if it were unlocking an invisible door in front of you.
A powerful A powerful wave of magic and energy erupt in the
air around the key.
A rift opens up around it, within which you can see the
stone frame of the mirror.
Beyond it lies the blackness of the shadow realm.
As the key and the necklace float toward you, you see that
the broken clasp of the necklace has been repaired. The necklace
fastens itself around your throat. throat. The key once again
hangs over your heart.
With the powerful spirit of the Soul Sword in your hand, you
step through the energy rift and enter the nightmare world of
the Shadow Realm.
The Shadow Realm is not the same as it was when you
left it. It is much worse.
Horrible Terrible screams and strange noises are sounding
everywhere.
Fires burn in the distance, and the twisted shadows of unknown
creatures are writhing around you in the firelight. It is like a
scene from a painting of hell.
Black clouds swirl about the jagged crescent of the destroyed
moon, making the shadow realm even darker than it was before the
red crystal is still lying at the base of the mirror it's
dim light is your only source of illumination wishing that it's
light were brighter you begin to reach for the crystal as if
in answer to your wish the crystal rises into the air and
slowly begins spinning spinning.
Rays of bright red light shoot out from the thousands of facets
that cover the surface of the spinning crystal.
The rays of light are also being reflected and intensified as
they flash across your mirrored liquid body.
The light is now bright enough for you to be able to
see the center of the shadow realm.
The motionless bodies of hundreds of dead ravens litter the once
white marble floor in the center of your domain.
The elemental statues have been hacked into strange,
surrealistic shapes.
The statues are now defaced monuments to the nightmare world
that the Shadow Realm has become.
The sun and moon pools are dried up and empty, their powerful
energies having long since vanished.
A huge shape suddenly appears at the edge of the shadows.
The shape slowly moves out of the shadows and into the light
of the crystal's crimson glow.
It is the dragon. This time, he is out for your blood.
The dragon lunges forward and snatches your arm and its huge
pointed teeth, But as it does, the living waters of your arm
separate and wash through the mouth of the beast. You are
uninjured.
The dragon rears backwards in confusion.
The living waters quickly reform and your arm is restored.
You now see that a single droplet of the living waters of
your arm is hovering in the air before the dragon.
The huge beast seems to be mesmerized by the shiny mirrored
droplet.
The droplet of living water begins to expand, and it transforms
into a double -sided reflective disk.
Just like the mirror, one side of this disk is capable of
deflecting energy, and the other side can become an open portal
that absorbs energy.
A single ray of light from the spinning crystal flashes over the
surface of the mirrored disk. It shines directly into the eyes
of the entranced dragon. The dragon cries out as if it has
been injured. It quickly retreats deep into a hidden recess
inside the Shadow Realm.
Intrigued by the power of this disc, you focus your mind on
its surface.
You are amazed by what you can see and feel.
You find that not only can you mentally command the disc's
movement,
but that you can also see in your mind what is being
reflected onto the mirrored surface of the disc.
You now know how to restore the Shadow Realm.
You quickly move back to the stone frame of the mirror and
step into the frame of the Looking Glass.
You mentally will the Spirit of the Soul Sword to move to
the other side of the mirror and wait for your command.
Obediently, the spirit of the soul sword leaves your hand and
moves to the opposite side of the mirror. It poises itself over
the empty frame as if ready to strike.
You now extend your arms and you shake and wave your hands,
releasing thousands of droplets droplets of the living waters
into the air.
Each droplet quickly transforms into a mirrored disc that hovers
above you in the shadow realm.
As if in response to what you are doing, the slowly spinning
red crystal grows brighter and brighter.
It begins to spin faster and faster. faster.
Its bright beams of light are reflecting off of the surfaces of
the mirrored disks, and the rays of light are penetrating deep
into the shadow realm.
Like the dragon, you can feel that the dark energies in the
shadow realm are retreating from the bright beams of light.
You release thousands more droplets of living water into the
air.
As you release the droplets of living waters from your hands,
you see that the tips of your fingers are returning to human
flesh.
You know that you must act quickly before your body changes back
to ordinary flesh and blood.
There are now thousands upon thousands of mirrored discs
scattered throughout the shadow realm.
You can see and feel that not only are the dark energies
within your domain retreating from the bright beams of light,
but that the deflective energies of the discs are pressing the
dark energies back toward the massive walls of stone that
surround the shadow realm.
The dark energies and forces are in retreat. retreat.
You deepen your concentration in the mirror discs, and as you
do, the rays of light emanating from the spinning crystal begin
locking onto the mirror discs and are holding them in place.
You are now mentally connected to each and every disc in the
shadow realm.
You command the disks to turn in unison.
The surfaces of the disks are now reversed. The living waters of
the disks begin to churn and flow like the ebbing tides, opening
thousands and thousands of portals within the shadow realm.
But you hold back the energies of the portals for just a
moment.
You know that whatever is pulled through these portals will also
have to pass through the living waters of your body as they
are drawn through the mirror frame.
You brace yourself for what is about to come.
You release your hold on the energy of the portals.
The dark forces and energies within the shadow realm are drawn
into the powerful vacuum of the mirrored discs.
The dark energies enter your liquid body, and as they do, the
horrible images of the dark energies flash through your mind,
but you are strong, stronger than you have ever been before.
The purity of your reborn spirit empowers you.
You face the horrible images in your mind, and by facing them,
you are removing their power.
One by one, the defeated energies disappear into the astral
world that lies beyond the stone frame of the mirror.
As each piece of dark energy passes through you, you can feel
the living waters of your body washing it, restoring the balance
to each of these forces as they pass. Drop by drop, the
living waters are returning to the mirror, and the sun side of
the looking glass is being restored.
The last dark energies are now passing through your body. You
feel the very last trace of them disappear beyond the portal of
the mirror. mirror.
You have defeated the dark energies, and you are empowered by
your victory.
Now it's time to command the Spirit of the Soul Sword to
strike.
It is still hovering on the opposite side of the mirror frame.
You command the sword to strike, and the sword thrusts forward
and pierces the waters of of the restored looking glass.
The powerful energies of creation within the spirit of the soul
sword spread over the surface of the looking glass.
The charged waters explode from the frame, filling the shadow
realm with their creative energies.
You look up to the skies of the shadow realm high above
you. The dying red star that was once the sun begins to
grow brighter and brighter.
Its powerful rays wash over the surface of the jagged crescent
of the moon.
As you watch, the sun and the moon are slowly restored.
The lights of the restored sun and moon intermingle and spread
throughout the shadow realm.
You watch with satisfaction as the sun and the moon slowly
disappear below the horizon.
The entire shadow realm has now been restored. restored.
You are finally able to relax in the twilight of your world.
You see that the spirit of the soul sword has returned to
the restored blade, which is once again frozen in the white
marble floor at the center of the shadow realm.
You step out of the mirror frame and as you do, the
living waters of the moon side of the looking glass are also
restored.
Now you notice a small red gemstone lying on the white marble
floor at your feet. feet.
You pick up this small stone and hold it in the palm
of your hand.
As you look closely at this stone, you see that thousands of
facets are cut into its surface.
Within each facet, you can see and feel all life within the
universe.
A bright light flashes over the stone and you see that the
imprint of the key that was burned into the palm of your
hand has been healed.
The stone floats up and away from your healed palm and embeds
itself into the shaft of the the key hanging over your heart.
You know that you have a powerful new tool, but its use
will have to wait for another day.
Although your mind is now at ease, you are very tired.
You slump, then sit on the white marble floor of the shadow
realm.
You can still feel the power of your rebirth flowing through
your mind and body
You grasp the key hanging over your heart with your hand It
is cool and soothing
You slowly begin to float up and away from the shadow realm
You float up and through the crystalline energies of the
restored circles of power, and their energies recharge your body
and spirit.
You slowly float higher and higher in your domain.
Just as you are about to leave your world, you look down
into the shadow realm and notice Notice that there are several
new additions to your domain.
A large wooden chest is sitting next to the moon pool, and
a chalice of silver and gold is resting on the edge of
the sun pool.
Next to the chalice is a very old bottle.
These new additions will also have to wait for another day.
It is time for you to rest now. Now, you continue your
ascent.
You are now crossing over the borders of the Shadow Realm.
As you pass over the borders, you see the statue of a
goddess standing behind the Moon Pool, and the statue of a god
behind the Sun Pool.
The gods and goddesses have returned to you. You cross the
boundaries of the shadow realm, and you open your eyes and your
mind to the waking world.
Thank you.